A Guide to the Papers of Martin Baskett Shepherd, 1817-1889
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Martin Baskett Shepherd, 1817-1889
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4241,-a
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given as a gift and a bequest on 1953 April 13 adn 1984 February 15.
Papers of Martin Baskett Shepherd,
- Correspondence
  - David Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1817-1819 (Box 1)
    - The treatment of the spavin of a horse by blistering and cantharious, or Spanish flies 1817 July 1
    - Fatherly advice on planning for the future and finding employment and news of the family 1819 April 4
  - Jesse Baskett Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1820 (Box 1)
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1820 June 3
      Economic hardships and having to sell his factory to John A. Cameron, the Presbyterian Church and it Sunday school, the benefit of the completed bridge to the trades.
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1820 July 23
      Advice on improving himself and recommendation to pursue Latin language studies; local news including a town election with candidates John A. Cameron and Gen. Davis, upcoming weddings, and Miss Catharine Elliot and her family.
  - Jesse Martin Baskett and Martin Baskett to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1822-1828, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Shelby County, Kentucky 1822 October 21
      Personal and family news, introduction of one cousin to another
    - Shelby County, Kentucky 1825 July 22
      Request to tend to a debt owed to Polly Kent
    - Shelby County, Kentucky 1828 September 16
      Advice for his nephew's "enlargement and prosperity in reasonable and religious matters"; family and local church-related news.
  - John Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1822-1831 (Box 1)
  - Augustine Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1827-1828 (Box 1)
    - Wadesboro, North Carolina 1827 November 20
      Plans for an upcoming trip to Nashville, Tennessee and New Orleans, Louisiana; family news; condition and prices of corn and cotton crops; "the present administration considered objectionable" in the district.
    - Wadesboro, North Carolina 1828 July 8
      Birth of son, Frederick Augustus, on May 7; decision to move family to Jackson City, Tennessee in hopes of good financial prospects
  - Letters to Martin Baskett Shepherd re Educational and Religious Issues 1821-1831 (Box 1)
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina, from John H. Norment and Thomas B. Lippitt 1821 June 2
      The progress of the "Society of our Little Place" and other religious societies; religious beliefs; limited news of Jesse and Augustine Shepherd.
    - Hartford, Connecticut, from Thomas H[opkins] Gallaudet (1781-1851) 1821 July 17
      Advice and information on stuttering from this educator
    - Montgomery County, North Carolina, from Armistead Lilly 1823 January 22
      Illness in that part of the country; increase in church membership and baptisms; teaching of religious beliefs
    - Albemarle County, Virginia, from P. Austin 1826 January 1
      Family and local news; Mr. William Bradford's school; expresses appreciation to his tutor.
    - Parsonage, from William Moore 1831 December 20
      Action of declining to accept the call to Fork Church due to accusations of some unnamed offense
  - Joseph Henry Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1829-1840 (Box 1)
    - Nashville, Tennessee 1829 November 1
      D[avid]; G[arland] Shepherd's school account; advice on and offer of assistance to purchase good land
    - Murfreesboro, Tennessee 1836 January 27
      Personal and family news; small pox vaccinations; opinions of the young ladies
    - Murfreesboro, Tennessee 1836 June 19
      Recurring attack of "ague & fever"; John Shepherd's improvement in health and diet; fear of the return of cholera; news of friends from Fluvanna County; Baptists, Presbyterians, and Methodists in the area; much drinking, little temperance; war with the Indians.
    - Nashville, Tennessee 1837 August 5
      Longing to return to Fluvanna County; an attack of bilious fever and inflamation of the lungs; lengthy discourse on "religious pretensions" and his "inclination to slight the goodness of God"
    - Nashville, Tennessee 1837 December 9
      Decline of yellow fever; personal and family news; Tennessee Baptist Convention; news of Robert Boyte Crawford Howell (1801-1868), Pastor of the First Baptist Church; church-related news
    - Huntsville, Alabama 1840 March 19
      Personal and family news; financial hardships; the need for an agent for the Baptist College; news of Pastor [Robert Boyte Crawford] Howell; church-related news.
  - David Garland Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1831-1849 (Box 1)
    - Jackson County, Tennessee 1831 October 17
      Good crops of corn but too wet for cotton and tobacco; the effects of competition on the goods business; personal news; the dissolution of the President's cabinet and fear that [Andrew] Jackson (1767-1845) would outlive his popularity; formation of temperance societies.
    - Granville, Tennessee 1838 September 17
      Death of their brother John Shepherd on the 13th from bilious fever and his longterm ill health; illnesses of John's wife Martha and daughter Sarah Baker; financial state of their business.
    - Granville, Tennessee 1838 November 5
      Death of child Sarah Baker Shepherd; advice on "removing west & to a nonslaveholding state."
    - Granville, Tennessee 1843 November 16, William Perkins living in New Orleans, Louisiana, Richard Smith replacing Perkins in Nashville, Tennessee, and his own business' loss of Smith; hardships of Martha Shepherd in supporting her family and her negroes, chiefly women and children; John Shepherd's estate.
    - Granville, Jackson County, Tennessee 1949 November 1
      Description of wife and children; Division of the Sons of Temperance, no liquor sold.
  - Correspondence of Martin Baskett Shepherd re Estate of David Shepherd 1833-1841 (Box 1)
    - Louisa, Virginia, from Thomas Baker 1833 May 25
      Advice not to sell the estate prior to their mother's death and explanation of provisions and special legacies in David Shepherd's will.
    - Louisa, Virginia, from Thomas Baker 1834 April 28
      Continued advice to not sell estate until "we can be perfectly safe."
    - New Glasgow, Virginia, from David S. Garland 1835 June 26
      Death of Mrs. Long, widow of David Shepherd; terms of disposition of negroes in David Shepherd's will; advice to sell negroes as they are selling at high prices and seeking assistance with the matter.
    - Wadesboro, North Carolina, from James M. [Shepherd] 1835 October 23
      Personal financial news; family news; John Shepherd's children being educated in South Carolina; inquiring into settlement of David Shepherd's estate; thoughts on abolition in South Carolina.
    - Albemarle County, Virginia, from Micajah Woods 1835 July 5
      Offering a proposition as to the disposition of the negroes belonging to Mrs. Long, widow of David Shepherd.
    - New Glasgow, Virginia, from David S. Garland 1837 September 3
      Disposition of a negro woman and child, living with Samuel M. Garland.
    - Yancey Mills, Albemarle County, Virginia, from John S. Cocke 1841 February 8
      Debt owed to David Shepherd's estate; purchase of a negro man and boy exhausting finances.
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1833-1847 (Box 1)
    - Palmyra, Virginia 1833 August 18
      Choice of Martin Shepherd as guardian
    - Nashville, Tennessee 1834 February 23
      Personal and family news; superior land in Kentucky and describing Shelby County, Kentucky as a good prospect in which to settle
    - Galveston, Texas [postmarked New Orleans, Louisiana] 1840 February 17
      The booming trade business; Mexican government's failure to recognize Texas' independence; northern provinces of Mexico commencing a revolt, President forbidding aid to Mexican provinces seeking independence; religious and church-related matters
    - Galveston, Texas [postmarked New Orleans, Louisiana] 1842 April 9
      Discussion of the last few months' invasion by the Mexicans; the current state of excitement among Texans and their strong feeling of independence; views on reasons for war; the effect of the dispute on business in Texas; personal and family news; church-related matters
    - Houston, Texas 1842 October 18
      Life in Houston, Texas; news of the Mexican rebellion against Texas; change in business status due to a dissolution of the partnership; personal and family news
    - Houston, Texas 1843 February 3
      Prospects in Texas worse for the time; expectation of a hostile demonstration by Mexico during the spring; the capture of about 250 "Texicans" in the town of Mier on the other side of the Rio Grande; view that the "Mexican nation cannot be regarded properly as a civilized people"; discourse on the Mexican population and the history of the separation of Texas; effect of rain on crops; discussion of "the perfidy of mankind"; personal and family news
    - Galveston, Texas [postmarked New Orleans, Louisiana] 1845 March 22
      Recovering from 1842 invasions by Mexico; doubts of the citizens of Texas over the proposition of annexation to the United States; personal and family news, improved business.
    - Houston, Texas [postmarked New Orleans, Louisiana] 1847 July 16
      Personal and family news; crops promising to be abundant, especially corn, sweet potatoes, and sugar cane; discussion of advantages and problems to moving out west; thoughts on the government's treatment of Mexico, Texas, and annexation.
  - James Meredith Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1836, 1843 (Box 1)
    - Wadesboro, Anson County, North Carolina 1836 January 22
      Plans to remove to Tennesee to be with their brother John; birth of Catherine Isabella Shepherd, daughter of Augustine Shephered, on December 20, 1835.
    - Granville, Jackson County, Tennessee 1843 June 28
      Personal and family news; David Shepherd in New Orleans now, in charge of a small lot of tobacco; his own tobacco crops doing poorly; state congressional and legislative elections.
  - Martha Ann Shepherd to Mary Kent Shepherd 1838, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Granville, Tennessee 1838 November 9
      Mourning the deaths of husband John and daughter Sarah Baker, her devastation over their loss.
    - Mention of an injury to Martin Shepherd's foot; John Newton Shepherd taking a professorship at Allegheny High School; personal and family news n.y. July 27
      W/ANS from John to Martin -- ill health; good corn crops; plans for cultivating cabbage, potatoes, tomatoes, and onions.
  - Robert Boyte Crawford Howell to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1838-1839 (Box 1)
    - Nashville, Tennessee 1838 October 23
      Acquaintance with Joseph Henry Shepherd, his good qualities, his religious beliefs having a strong Presbyterian influence, the effect of his brother John's death on his spirits.
    - Nashville, Tennesse 1839 March 19
      News of Joseph Henry Shepherd's baptism in the waters of the Cumberland and joining the Church.
  - Mrs. E. O. Mitchell to Mary Kent Shepherd 1838-1848 (Box 1)
    - 1838 May 29
      Personal and family news, particularly in relation to health and religion
    - Mitchell's Store, Virginia 1839 March 1
      Personal and family news; schooling of E[ ] L[acy] and Harriet Baker, and her studies in natural philosophy, astronomy, and use of the globes; visit by [James] Fife; intentions of having a school.
    - Mitchell's Store, Virginia 1840 October 11
      Personal and family news; religious matters
    - Mitchell's Store, Virginia 1841 June 19
      Sympathy and religious and spiritual support for death of a child of Mary Kent Shepherd; personal and family news.
    - Mitchell's Store, Virginia 1843 March 3
      From C. S. Farrar, on the circumstances and death of her mother; death of cousin Polly Farrar; w/ANS from Mrs. E. O. Mitchell, on the death of her mother
    - Mitchell's Store, Virginia 1844 April 11
      Illness, treatment, and death of Virginia on March 8th
    - [ ]sville, Virginia 1848 December 14
      Personal and family news
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd to Mary Kent Shepherd 1839-1841 (Box 1)
    - New Orleans, Louisiana 1839 April 19
      Personal and family news; grateful for their religious and spiritual support in his time of doubt, envious of their brother's newfound faith and baptism; the growth of Galveston, Texas with its fertile land and fine climate
    - Galveston, Texas [postmarked New Orleans, Louisiana] 1841 October 17
      Death of newborn and his wife's subsequent problems with drying up her milk; yellow fever in New Orleans; soil and climate of [New Orleans]; growth of churches, with Presbyterian, Methodist, Episcopalian, and Catholic buildings in progress; the conquest of Texas; w/ANS to Martin Shepherd -- good deal of shipping and business from other ports; the fluctuation of Texas government liabilities
  - Letters to Martin Baskett Shepherd re Educational or Religious Issues 1840-1859 (Box 1)
    - Winnsville, from J. Winn 1840 October 23
      Suggestion to write a piece on "the impropriety of the interference of the Pastor of a Church in political matters"; supporting the cause of "true religion" without political ties.
    - From R. H. Raymond 1845 November 14
      "The plan of classing scholars in grammar so as successfully to advance them"; discussion of scholars, named by initials, and their progress.
    - R. H. Raymond [1845?]
      The examination of J. G. Hughes
    - Sandy River, from Daniel Witt 1846 May 4
      Declining an invitation from Fork Church for Witt to preach; interest in the large churches under his ministry
    - To James B. Taylor, from M[artin]; B[askett] Shepherd 1852 August 21
      Views on the community as a whole in regard to religion and the success of the [Fork] church in gaining membership
    - To William A. Whitescarver, from [Martin Baskett Shepherd] 1853 January 7
      Increasing the membership of the Fork Church; the current condition of the Fork Church as being somewhat fragile; personal religious
    - Receipt from William Tompkins, Superintendent of Schools, Fluvanna County, for balance of school funds 1853 January 24
    - Chesterfield Court House, from Harriet A. Baker 1856 August 12
      Pursuing a teaching position at Winnsville Institute
    - Richmond, Virginia, from H. K. Ellyson 1856 June 17
      Enclosing the Abstract of the Annual Report of the State Mission Board and soliciting funds.
    - Charlottesville, Virginia, from A. P. Abell 1859 April 22
      Seeking the work of "private Christians" to spread the word of the Baptists
    - Concord, [North Carolina], from James D. Coleman 1859 December 7
      The Goshen Association, its election of delegates to the Richmond Convention, and its election of delegates to the Biennial Convention in 1856 and its directive to the Board to fill the vacancies, [James Madison] Pendleton (1811-1891) and the influence of [James Robinson] Graves (1820-1893) and the Tennessee Baptist.
    - From M[ary]; K[ent]; S[hepherd]n.d.
      Religious support to a friend
    - From A. J. Goolsby n.d.
      Appreciation of kind advice and interest in welfare
  - Jesse George Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1841-1851 (Box 1)
    - Raleigh, North Carolina 1841 July 26
      Personal and family news, particularly re Benjamin A. Shepherd and James Meredith Shepherd; attending the Law School; comments on the ladies, gentlemen, and families in Raleigh; detailed description of a visit to Monticello and Thomas Jefferson's burial ground; travel through Charlottesville, Gordonsville, and Richmond (by railroad to North Carolina); good corn crops, bad grain; life in Raleigh, North Carolina; the growth of the college at Chapel Hill.
    - Raleigh, North Carolina 1842 April 14
      Thoughts of marriage this spring season; temperance societies being formed and being opposed by the Episcopalians; Whig Convention of April 1842, where Mr. [Henry] Clay (1777-1852) was nominated for the Presidency and Governor [John Motley] Morehead (1796-1866) for reelection
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1843 March 20
      Marriage of James [Shepherd] to Eliza I. Strother of Smith County, Tennessee; impending marriage to Catherine Isabella Dobbin, and having $1,500 to $2,000, 13 negroes and a good library; description of the Dobbin family members; the growth of Fayetteville
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1844 December 20
      Married and family life, living with mother-in-law; owning 6 negro men, two young girls and two young women who have 5 children; principal crop in area is corn; wanting his own farm; improvements in the science of agriculture; rich lands in the state and the land on the Roanoke first rate, good corn and cotton crops.
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1845 December 17
      Promotion of "Extra Billy" [William Smith (1797-1887), governor of Virginia, 1846-1849]; James C[ochran] Dobbin (1814-1857), a member of congress from that district, and his taking over Dobbins' clients; town recovering from a disastrous fire in June; wanting his own farm and having to hire out his negroes at present; best business is steam mill timber and turpentine.
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1850 April 1
      Releases his own interest in his grandparents' estate; personal and family news
    - Fayetteville, North Carolina 1851 November 9
      Personal and family news--new baby daughter, the four children, Henry Elliot, Margaret Dobbin, Kate and Mary; large legal practice with circuit in four counties, their residence on the "Sand Hills," the girls Marg[aret] Ann, Sarah, and Kate
  - James Fife to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1843-1848 (Box 1)
    - Receipt for Virginia Baptist S. S. and Public Association 1843 June 6
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1845 December 17
      Death of Bro. Smith in the Fluvanna County area
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1848 March 2
      Lengthy religious opinions on man and his actions concerning "Negroe trading" and the condemnation [by the Baptist Church] for men trading negroes for gain
  - David S. Shepherd to John Newton Shepherd 1845 (Box 1)
    - Louisa Court House, Virginia 1845 February 8
      Personal news
  - William M. Perkins to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1845, 1850 (Box 1)
    - Byrd, Columbia, Virginia 1845 December 11
      Wanting to get together while he is at his father's
    - New Orleans, Louisiana 1850 April 10
      Occupied with business; personal and family news; Robert Boyte Crawford Howell leaving Nashville Church
  - Martin Baskett Shepherd to Isaac O. Perkins 1846-1847 (Box 1)
    - Religious contemplation of man's place in the world, and his own state of "darkness, doubt & despondency" 1846 January 1
    - Lengthy discourse on "the proper manner of examining candidates for baptism" 1847 October 17
  - A. B. Smith to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1846-1847 (Box 1)
    - Richmond, Virginia 1846 October 16
      The late Brother Smith's memoirs and inquiries as to Brother Smith's general character
    - Fluvanna, Virginia, from Martin Baskett Shepherd 1847 April 11
      The late Bro. Smith's general character and his involvement in politics
    - Richmond, Virginia 1847 July 13
      The late Brother Smith, his memoirs, and his involvement in politics
  - D. F. Newton to John Newton Shepherd and Martin Baskett Shepherd 1849-[1850] (Box 1)
    - Covington, Kentucky 1849 April 31
      Religious thoughts
    - Covington, Kentucky ca. 1850
  - O. T. Mitchell to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1850 (Box 1)
    - Poet's Hill, Virginia 1850 December 30
      Inquiring about the condition of "Winnsville" and the probability of it being sold.
  - James Fife to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1850-1852 (Box 1)
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1850 June 14
      Harvesting and being unable to deliver guano to him; news of David F. Newton who has abandoned ties with the church and become an active abolitionist; the good qualities of [ ] Broaddus as a preacher.
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1851 November 19
      The benefits of giving Shepherd's son a good education; lengthy discussion of farming, giving much instruction, and the rewards of farming; the Baptist church
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1852 February 3
      Church-related news; lengthy discourse on the effects of abolitionism on blacks and whites, especially in regard to church and worship
    - Fluvanna, Virginia, from Martin Baskett Shepherd 1852 February 9
      Church-related and religious discussion
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1852 June 17
      Mention of [ ] Broaddus and John Newton; "the large concourse of Black and White who cannot get in at the Fork Union," his disppointment in the church, and his schemes on how to construct a larger house
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1852 September 6
      Gratification of hard labor in restoring faith in the brethren; mention of Brothers Broaddus and Whitescarver
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1852 October 14
      Good qualities of Brother Whitescarver
    - Charlottesville, Virginia 1852 July 27
      Hardships of being ill with dyspepsia and trying to find relief, and various suggestions for the relief of symptoms
    - Letters in The Herald signed "Aquila" being attributed to a young preacher by the name of Thomas of Nelson; advice on leaving a controversial matter alone and leaving the matter to a counsel n.d.
    - From Martin Baskett Shepherd n.d., (incomplete)
      Church-related news; discord in the church
  - Benjamin A. Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1850-1854 (Box 1)
    - Houston, Texas 1850 April 22
      Personal and family news, including his being ill with asthma, his children's health, and the improved health of Constantine; inquiries on whether or not he will stay in Fluvanna and advice on buying land; thinks that "a man with negroes can make more at farming and stock raising" in Texas; financial matters and settlement of their mother's estate
    - Houston, Texas 1851 February 12
      His own improved health and two of his children afflicted with "rheumatism or nervous weakness"; the Compromise of 1850 and the effects on emigration and Texas; life in Texas; offer to assist with the purchase of land...
    - Houston, Texas 1853 June 10
    - New York, New York -- 1853 July 29
    - Houston, Texas 1854 March 29
    - Houston, Texas 1854 June 30
    - Houston, Texas 1854 July 13
    - Houston, Texas 1854 August 11
    - Houston, Texas 1854 August 25
    - Houston, Texas 1854 September 8
    - Houston, Texas 1854 September 25
    - Houston, Texas 1854 October 31
  - Thomas Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1851, 1856 (Box 1)
    - Fluvanna, Virginia 1851 July 16
      Request from George A. Bowles for permission from John Newton to go to Hampden Sydney College; guardianship of their niece ["Kate"]
    - Fluvanna, Virginia 1856 June 8
      Personal and family news; administration of the mercantile business of Mr. H. Payne
  - Augustine Shepherd to Martin Baskett Shepherd 1851, 1861 (Box 1)
  - Wadesboro, North Carolina 1851 July 20 (Box 1)
    Plans for the care and guardianship of "Kate"
    - Wadesboro, North Carolina 1857 April 27
      Personal and family news; inquiries as to the standing of the Virginia Female Institute; cotton crops, scarcity of provisions
    - Wadesboro, North Carolina 1861 May 20
      "the movements of troops and preparation for war"; support of the South
  - Letters to John Newton Shepherd 1852-1854 (Box 1)
    1852 August 20, from F[lavius]; J[oseph] Ribble -- studies at the University of Virginia; Dr. [Gessner] Harrison's work on Latin Grammar [ An Exposition of some of the Laws of the Latin Grammar]; choosing a room on the Lawn as opposed to the Western Range; expectations of laborious studies